“这房子装修的可真漂亮，夫人! ”
[Harshad] 'What a lovely house you've made, my lady!'
在这里建一个露台花园
We'll build a terrace garden here.
- 你知道，那些小型植物和树木?-盆景
- You know, with those miniature plants and trees? - Bonsai.
‘盆景，我听说会带来幸运’
[Harshad] 'Bonsai. We'll plant those too. I've heard they are very lucky.'
怎么了？
What is it?
你没事吧？
Is everything okay?
我该说什么？
What do I say?
你告诉我，你工作还好吗？
You tell me. Is everything okay at work?
什么意思？
What do you mean?
你的业务超出了我的理解范围
Your business is beyond my understanding.
但是我知道所有的报纸都在报道你
But I do understand that all the newspapers are writing about you.
那就让他们报道吧
So let them.
毫无价值的新闻
It's worthless news.
多亏了你丈夫，许多家庭才得以经营
Many homes run thanks to your husband, my lady.
新闻记者就是其中之一
News reporters are amongst them.
-就让他们也赚点钱吧-我害怕
- So, let them earn too. - I'm scared.
这次感觉不一样了
It feels different this time.
有什么不同？
What's different?
- 你想太多了-嘿！
- You think too much. - Hey!
我不会占用太多的时间
'I won't take up too much of your time.'
我知道... ..
'I know...'
“ ... 你们中的大多数人在这里... ”
'...that most of you are here...'
只为了听一个人的话
'...to listen to just one man.'
据我所知，他是个科学家
According to me, he's a scientist.
股票市场的爱因斯坦
Einstein of the share market.
哈尔沙德 · 梅塔
Harshad Mehta. Please, come.
谢谢你
Thank you.
老实说，我连爱因斯坦这个词都拼不出来
To be honest, I can't even spell 'Einstein'.
不过没关系
But that's okay.
很新鲜
It's new.
这些天，人们也叫我股市的小偷
These days, people are also calling me the thief of the stock market.
报纸称我为“大牛” ..
The newspapers refer to me as "Big Bull"...
“大牛带着印度国家银行的50亿卢比跑了”
"Big Bull has run away with 500 crores from SBI."
这意味着我吞掉了 SBI 的50亿
They mean I have swallowed up SBI's 500 crore.
如果我不得不吞下钱，为什么只有50亿？
If at all I had to swallow money, why just 500 crores?
什么？
Huh?
货币市场设立了一个每日自助餐... 两万亿卢比
The money market sets up a daily buffet... of two lakh crores.
所以想象一下，哈尔沙德 · 梅塔的日常交易会是什么样子！
So imagine. What Harshad Mehta's daily transactions would be!
但他们不会以我的名字命名
But they aren't taking my name.
他们只是写“大牛”
They just write "Big Bull".
大家都知道，我是大公牛
Well, everyone knows, I am the Big Bull.
“嗯? ”
[Harshad] 'Hmm?'
但是，我大公牛与安全交易有什么关系呢？
But what does my being the Big Bull have to do with the reconciliation of security transactions?
间接地说，他们想表达的是..
Indirectly what they're trying to say is...
我要为市场的牛市负责
...that I am responsible for the bull run in the market.
好吧，没关系
Okay. That's fine.
但这也意味着... 如果不是因为我..
But that also means... if it wasn't for me...
市场会像牛车一样缓慢前进吗？
...the market would be lumbering along at the pace of a bullock cart?
实际上报纸没有证据
The truth is that the newspapers have no proof.
这就是为什么他们没有公开我的名字
That's why they aren't taking my name openly.
因为他们说的都是假话
Because there's no truth in what they're saying.
我从 SBI 拿了50亿卢比
I took 500 crores from SBI.
是的，是真的
Yes, it's true. I did.
但我也把它退了回去
But I also returned it.
就算登报了又怎样？
How about printing that? Hmm?
但他们不会
But they won't.
因为，如果它不是负面的，它就不是新闻
Because, if it's not negative, it's not news.
报纸需要卖出去，不是吗？
The newspaper needs to sell, right?
他们也需要赚钱糊口，不是吗？
They too have homes to run, don't they?
但是他们毫无根据的新闻吓不倒我
But their baseless and biased news doesn't scare me.
我为什么要害怕？
Why should I be scared?
因为我打破了外资银行在货币市场的垄断地位？
Because I've broken the monopoly of foreign banks in the money market?
在孟买..
In Mumbai...
每天早上当股票市场的钟声敲响的时候
...every morning when the gong is struck at the stock market...
我的名字也随之被吟诵
...my name is chanted along with it.
这里是孟买
This is Bombay.
在这里，一切都会改变..
Here, everything will change...
但海洋永远在那里
...but the ocean will always be there.
所以，我就是达拉街（印度华尔街）的海洋
So, I am the ocean of Dalal Street.
如果你有胆量，你就能尝到盐的味道
If you have the guts, you can taste the salt.
他们说交易所将在二十八号重新开放
They say the market will reopen on the 28th.
罢工即将结束
The strike will be over.
如果印度证交所主席已经接受了他们的要求... ..
If the SEBI chairman had already accepted their demands...
那为什么要把罢工拖延这么久？
...then what was the point of stretching the strike on for so long?
-阿什温，我觉得...-你的想法完全正确
- Ashwin Bhai, I think... - Your thoughts are absolutely right, Bhushan.
这篇文章的发表，这次罢工的延续..
The publishing of this article, the extension of the strike...
这一切都计划得太周密，时机也太巧妙了
It's all been too well-planned and timed.
因此，只要一开市，股价就会持续下跌
So that, as soon as the market opens the sentiment is low and it crashes...
你和我都明白，但我们都是笨蛋，对吧？
You and I get it, but we are duffers, right?
但是这个家伙..
But this fellow...
一个天才,
...a genius,
股市的“爱因斯坦”
"Einstein" of the market.
他已经飘了，看看他
His brain has stopped working. Look at him.
你应该听听他的演讲
You should've heard his speech.
那个苏切塔 · 达拉尔没有任何名字
That Sucheta Dalal didn't take any names.
但是他... 他公开承认..
But he... he confessed publicly...
“我就是市场的大公牛”
"I am the Big Bull of the market."
- 大家为他鼓掌-罪犯才会招供
- A round of applause for him. - Confessions are made by criminals.
我只陈述事实
I only stated facts.
这也只是为了没有人能够反对我们
And that too, only so that nobody can take a stand against us.
我说的有什么不对吗？
And what is wrong with what I said?
我们要隐瞒什么? 我要隐瞒什么？
What do we have to hide? What should I hide?
现在，即使是 SBI 也确认他们已经收到了资金
Now, even SBI has confirmed that they've received their money.
怎么了? 有什么问题吗？
So? What's the issue?
那么，你为什么不也告诉大家，偿还 SBI 的钱从哪里来呢？
Then, why don't you also tell everyone where the money to repay SBI came from?
- 对吧?-阿什温
- Right? - Ashwin Bhai...
(拉杰迪普)“因此，我是说这不是头版新闻”
[Rajdeep] 'Therefore, I was saying it's not a front-page story.'
接下来的故事会是怎样的？
What will the follow-up story be?
哈尔沙德承认他从 SBI 那里拿了钱
Harshad is admitting that he took money from SBI.
即使在我看来，这似乎是他与银行打交道的日常事务
'Even to me, it seems like a daily deal that he does regularly with banks.'
就连印度国家银行的官员也在说同样的话
'Even SBI officials are saying the same thing.'
很快，人们就会质疑我们..
Soon, people are going to question us...
质疑我们的动机！
...about our motive!
哈尔沙德让我们看起来像个八卦杂志
Harshad is making us look like a f*****g gossip magazine.
- 但是哈尔沙德需要被绳之以法...-听我说，苏切塔
- But Harshad needs to be brought to justice... - Listen to me, Sucheta.
哈尔沙德是一个英雄，一个普通人眼中的英雄
Harshad is a hero. A hero for the common man.
他在为他的客户、投资人赚钱
His clients, his investors. He's making profits for them.
人们倾向于相信他所说的一切
People are inclined to believe whatever he says...
不管我们怎么写他
...in spite of what we write against him.
[拉杰迪普]“相反，你为什么不写... ... ”
[Rajdeep] 'Instead, why don't you write about...'
“ ... ... 永无休止的经纪人罢工? ”
'...the never-ending brokers' strike at the BSE?'
- 你到底在说什么，拉杰迪普?-是啊
- What are you even saying, Rajdeep? - Yeah.
不，这是个好故事，你知道的
No. This is a good story and you know it.
我想你们一定读过《印度时报》上的那篇文章吧？
I'm sure you've read the article that appeared in Times of India?
是的，市场上的大公牛和证券问题
Yes, sir. The Big Bull and the securities reconciliation issue.
大公牛
- Big Bull! -[smirks]
真不戳! 有什么新鲜事吗？
Great! So, what's new?
我们知道这会发生，但是我们什么也没做
We knew this could happen. And yet, we did nothing.
我们已经怀疑了一年了
We were suspecting this for a year, now.
先生，我们去年已经发布了指导方针，但是..
Sir, we had issued guidelines last year, sir but...
什么指导方针？
What... What guidelines are we talking about?
这个？
This one?
”从 PDO 返回 SGL 表格的任何实例... ”
"Any instance of return of SGL form from the PDO..."
” ... 因为帐户缺少足够的余额... ”
"...for want of sufficient balance in the account..."
“ ... ... 应立即通知储备银行... ... ”
"...should be immediately brought to the Reserve Bank's notice..."
” ... 所有交易的细节”
"...with the details of the transactions."
我敢肯定，一半的银行根本没看过
I'm sure, half the people didn't even get it.
剩下一半
And the rest...
他们直接用来擦屁股
They just wiped and flushed it.
[穆克吉]“先生... ... ”
[Mukherjee] 'Sir...'
我们该怎么办，先生？
How do we proceed, sir?
利用你在每家银行的信息来源
Use your sources with every bank.
还有... ... 进行一次粗略的审计
[Venkitarajan] 'And... Conduct a rough audit.'
看看这些垃圾已经传播了多远..
Find out how far this garbage has spread...
然后我们就会知道这个骗局的严重程度
...and then we will know the extent of this scam...
苏切塔..
Sucheta...
听着..
Look...
拉杰迪普是对的
...Rajdeep is right.
请别介意，但是..
Please don't mind, but...
我觉得我们太着急了
...I think we rushed the story.
我们? 为什么是”我们” ? 你可以直接怪我
We? Why "we"? You can blame me directly.
我不是在怪你，苏切塔，我不是在怪你
I'm not blaming you, Sucheta. I'm not blaming.
我只是说也许..
I was just saying, that maybe...
如果我们多调查一些..
...if we had investigated more...
多研究一点，然后我们可以..
...researched a bit more then we could've...
我的意思是... 如果我们能找到..
See, what I mean is that... if we could have found someone...
愿意公开声明的人，那我们就有..
...who was willing to go on record then we'd have...
我在一家日报社工作
Debashis, I work for a daily newspaper.
我不像你一样为杂志社工作
I don't work for a magazine, like you...
我可以坐下来好好思考，因为我有几个星期的时间交稿
...that I can sit back and think because I have a few weeks.
我每天都有最后期限
I have a deadline, daily.
如果我再继续等，就不会有这样的故事了
If I'd have waited, I wouldn't have had a story.
你知道哈尔沙德 · 梅塔是个该死的骗子
You know Harshad Mehta is a bloody scamster.
你知道吗? 如果他们想要一个该死的后续..
You know what? If they want a goddamn follow up...
- 我会找到的-苏切塔，听着
- ...I am gonna find one. - Sucheta, listen.
苏切塔，你……
Sucheta... Look, you...
如果你生我的气，可以让我离开
[Debashis] 'If you are mad at me, I'll leave.'
你为什么要离开自己的房子？
Why are you leaving your own house?
别这样，苏切塔
Come on, Sucheta.
[苏切塔]“交易所终于重新开放了”
[Sucheta] 'Finally the market opened.'
“我仍然没有任何针对哈萨德的书面证据”
'I still had no paper evidence against Harshad.'
但是他已经提前承认了这篇文章是关于他的
'But he had gone ahead and admitted that the article was about him.'
[ Sucheta ]“他试图淡化自己与 SBI 之间的问题... ... ”
[Sucheta] 'He was trying to downplay his problems with SBI...'
希望市场不会有反应
'...in the hope that the markets would not react...'
“但是人们似乎对哈尔沙德失去了信任”
'...but it seemed that the people had lost trust in Harshad.'
[ Sucheta ]“高摩资本投资的股票直线下跌... ... ”
[Sucheta] 'It was a free fall for the shares in which Growmore was investing...'
如果不能保持在4000点，它将进一步下跌
If it doesn't hold at 4000, it will drop further.
- 啊?-不是你，是 Sensex 指数
- Huh? - Not you. The Sensex.
这太过分了
This is too much.
没有机会了，拉凯什
There's no chance, Rakesh.
即使今天仍然如此
Even if it holds today...
再过几天就会跌到3000以下
...in a few days, it'll drop below 3000.
下降的轨迹才刚刚开始，兄弟
The downward trajectory has only just started, brother.
等着瞧吧
Wait and watch.
这一次，哈沙德完蛋了
This time, Harshad is finished.
我们不应该草率行事，大肆收购
We shouldn't be hasty and go on a buying spree.
我们必须像狐狸一样悄悄行动
We have to be stealthy, like a fox.
听着，这次我们很幸运
Look. This time, we were lucky.
我们所有的损失都将转化为利润
All our losses will get converted into profits.
没错...血赚一笔
True... Our a***s were on fire!
还好我们只签了一些……
It's good we only singed some p*bes.
你控制不了你的舌头，也控制不了你的膀胱
You have no control over your tongue, nor your bladder.
- 我只是...-胡说八道！
- I was just... - What nonsense!
我..
I...
我们这次勉强活了下来，但这次不能再这样下去了
We scraped through this time but this can't go on.
我觉得..
I think...
现在是退休的好时机
...this is the right time to get out of this casino and retire.
- 退休?-你在说什么？
- Retire? - What are you saying?
我们计划了这一切，只是为了留在市场上
We planned all this, only to stay in the market.
你是说要离开市场？
And you're talking of leaving the market?
我说的不是离开市场
I'm not talking about leaving the market.
今天我决定..
Today, I have decided...
把自己从这些糟心交易中解放出来
...to free myself from this trading mess.
如果我需要刺激，我可以去拉斯维加斯
If I need excitement, thrill, I'll go to Vegas.
对吧？
Right?
从现在开始，只做价值投资
From now on, only value investing.
价值投资
Just value investing.
还有..
And...
我会选好的公司，好的股票..
I'll pick good companies, good shares...
投入大量资金，然后等待长远的发展
...invest big amounts... ...and just wait for long term.
日复一日的投机交易都是胡说八道
Day to day trading is nonsense.
专注于伟大的梦想..
Focus on the big dream...
然后赚几百万
...and make millions.
- 也许几十亿-也许几万亿
- Maybe billions. - Maybe trillions.
你们在说什么？
What are you guys talking about?
这是在市场上交易的最佳时机
This is the perfect time to trade in the market.
梅塔很快就会退出市场
Look, Mehta will soon be out of the market.
Sensex 指数将从3000点跌至2500点
Sensex will drop from 3000 to 2500.
在那之后，利润就来自于购买
And after that, the profit lies in buying.
你看，我不能简单地解释长期的故事
See, I can't explain the story of long-term in short.
在20到25年内，市场将上升到..
In 20 to 25 years, the market will rise to...
三万五到四万
...35,000 to 40,000.
它不会从3000变成零
It's not going to go from 3000 to zero.
现在是做公牛的时候了
This is the time to be a bull.
熊队的日子一去不复返了
Gone are the days of playing Bears and nibbling peanuts.
- 嘿，兄弟...-别跟我说”嘿，兄弟” ，我在讲道理
- Hey, Bhai... - Don't "Hey Bhai" me, I'm talking sense.
如果我的预测是正确的..
If my prediction is correct...
谁知道呢，我可能会成为下一个大公牛
...then who knows, I could be the next Big Bull.
当然
Sure.
“现在已经跌破4000了”
[Bhushan] 'We're past 4000 now.'
Sensex指数已经触底了
The market has sunk so low... ...the Sensex is scraping the floor.
股票市场变成了杂鱼市场
The share market has turned into a fish market.
你在听吗？
Are you listening?
直到去年，每个人都在买入
Up until last year, everyone was buying.
而现在，突然之间，整个世界都在卖出
And today, all of a sudden, the whole world is selling.
我们的客户都吓呆了
Our jobbers were petrified.
好像他们要被愤怒的人群殴打似的
As if they were going to be bashed up by the angry crowd.
- 每个人都很害怕-他们当然害怕
- Everyone is scared. -[Ashwin] 'Of course they are scared.'
为什么不害怕呢
'Why won't they be scared?'
市场下跌了500多点
The market has dropped by more than 500 points.
还有Polo... Polo一下子从510下降到了300
And Polo... Polo has dropped to 510 from 300 in a snap.
- 兄弟我们得赶紧想个策略-策略？
- Brother, we need to think of a strategy soon. - Strategy?
什么样的策略？
What kind of strategy?
我们现在只剩下希望了
All we are running on, is hope.
而且希望也快用没了
And we're slowly losing that too.
先想想我们要怎么偿还 NHB 的钱？
Now start thinking how will we repay NHB's money?
这是你第一次看到股市下跌吗？
Is this the first time you are seeing the market fall?
(哈沙德)“已经很长时间没有开盘了，很明显会下跌”
[Harshad] 'It has opened after a long time. It's obvious it'll dip.'
拂去一些灰尘，然后再次升起
It'll lick some dust and rise again.
你忘了吗? 我们是从坠机开始的
And have you forgotten? We started with a crash.
“有什么新鲜事吗? ”
[Harshad] 'What's new about it?'
最新情况是，哈沙德，这次... ..
What's new, Harshad, is that this time...
我们就是坠机的原因
...we are the reason for the crash.
那更好，我们是市场之王
Even better. We're the kings of the market.
如果我们可以让它下跌，那我们也可以让它再涨上去
If we can cause it to fall, we can make rise it too.
风向对哈尔沙德有利
The wind is blowing in Harshad's favour.
它会在我们的命令下改变方向
And it will change its course on our command.
现在在这次事故之后，我们要怎么还钱？
And now after this crash, how will we return Pherwani's money?
你知道这个数目有多大，对吧？
You do know how big the amount is, don't you?
我可以进来吗，先生
[Kashmira] 'May I come in, sir?'
卡什米拉，我告诉过你我今天不想被打扰
Kashmira, I told you I don't want to get disturbed today.
对不起，先生，拉希尔先生在线上
Sorry, sir. But, Mr. Rahil is on the other line...
他坚持要和你谈谈
...and he insists on talking to you.
- 帮我接通-好的先生
- Connect me. - Okay, sir.
你好，拉希尔
Hello, Rahil.
- 你好吗?-我... 我很好
- How are you? - I'm... I'm fine.
你看到市场的情况了吗？
Have you seen the condition of the market?
是的，然后呢？
Yes. So?
不，我的意思是... ... 你的人让我投资... ..
[Rahil] 'No, I mean... your men asked me to invest...'
我把我所有的钱都投进去了，我现在被套牢了
...and I did. I invested all I had. I'm deep in it now.
拉希尔，股市有时会震荡
Rahil, I call the stock market, shock market sometimes.
它可以造成真正的打击
It can deal a real blow.
有时可以赚钱，有时要遭受损失
At times you make a profit, at times you incur a loss.
这就是市场，对吧？
That's what business means, right?
你在教我做事？
You're lecturing me about the market?
我对股票市场了解多少？
What do I know about the stock market?
你说，你的人说... ‘投资，投资，投资... ’所以，我照做了
You said, your men said... 'Invest, invest, invest...' So, I did.
现在一切都完了
[Rahil] 'It's all over now.'
拉希尔，这是股市不是金库
Rahil, this is the stock market not a treasure chest...
不是把手伸进去，就能抽出一大笔钱来
...that you dip your hand and pull out a fortune, when you like.
你投资的这些钱，是你在市场上赚来的，对吗？
And this money that you invested, you earned it in the market, right?
所以，市场收回了一部分
So, the market took some of it back.
“我没拿你的钱”
[Harshad] 'I didn't take your money.'
我明白你的意思，但是..
I... I get your point, but...
听着，拉希尔，你是我的朋友... ... 所以我要耐心地解释
Look Rahil, you are a friend... ...so I'm explaining patiently.
我有很多客户
I have many clients.
我不能向每个人解释，是吗？
I can't explain to each one, can I?
我们改天再聊
We'll talk peacefully some other time.
布尚，不要在这里抽烟！
Bhushan, don't smoke here!
[ Tyagi ]“那么，今天 Sensex 指数跌了多少? ”
[Tyagi] 'So, how much did the Sensex fall today?'
- 下降了570点-哇
- Fell by 570 points. - [Tyagi] 'Wow.'
准确地说，是12.77%
That's 12.77 per cent to be precise.
在证交所的历史上从来没有..
Never before in the history of BSE...
在一天之内下降这么多
...has it dropped so much in a single day.
[ AK ]“投资者的财富蒸发了10% 以上”
[AK] 'That's more than 10 percent investor wealth wiped out.'
我相信，他们中的大多数都是哈沙德的投资者
And I believe, most of them are Harshad's investors.
嗯..
Hmm...
然而，哈尔沙德设法偿还了印度国家银行的贷款
And yet, Harshad managed to repay SBI.
一共50亿卢比
All 500 crores.
我只是想知道是谁资助他的？
I just wonder who funded him?
不管是谁，很快就会暴露
Whoever it was, will be exposed soon.
我相信sensex指数也会在议会上讨论
I believe the sensex will be discussed in the Parliament too.
- 你确定?-非常确定
- Are you sure? - Pretty sure.
政客们都在关注这个，AK
Politicians are on this, AK.
哈尔沙德从市场上拿走了太多的钱
Harshad has taken too much money from the market.
[ Tyagi ]‘他必须全部归还，今年秋天... ... ’
[Tyagi] 'And he has to return it all. And due to this fall...'
他的财产减少了一半
...his holdings have been halved.
是时候结束哈尔沙德 · 梅塔的故事了
It's time to put an end to this Harshad Mehta story.
今天国会议员们就..
'Today the members of the parliament debated...'
’ ... 昨天股票市场的突然崩盘... ’
'...the sudden crash at the stock market yesterday...'
“ ... ... 导致了史上最大的 Sensex 指数下跌”
'...that resulted in the biggest Sensex fall ever.'
在反对派领导人的压力下... ..
'Under pressure from the opposition leaders...'
政府宣布
'...the government announced...'
“ ... RBI 将调查这一事件... ”
'...that RBI will probe the event...'
今天，我们的成员..
'Today, the members of the...'
- 喂?-哈沙德..
- Hello? - Harshad...
仔细听我说
Listen to me carefully.
你的15天结束了
[Pherwani] 'Your 15 days are over.'
我要拿回我的钱
I need my money back.
斐尔瓦尼先生，你为什么这么担心？
Pherwani ji, why do you worry so much?
让我来考虑这些事
Worrying is my job.
我欠你钱，你会得到的
I owe you the money and you'll get it.
哈沙德，你不明白
Harshad, you are not understanding.
印度储备银行成立了一个调查委员会..
RBI has formed an enquiry committee...
检查你与 SBI 的交易
...to inspect your transactions with the SBI.
你明白这意味着什么吗
[Pherwani] 'Do you understand what this means?'
这意味着这些家伙随时可能出现在我家门口
It means that these guys can land up any time at my doorstep.
[ Pherwani ]“我不想那样”
[Pherwani] 'And I don't want that.'
我要我的账簿干干净净，就这样
I want my books clean, that's it.
[ Pherwani ]“要么你筹集资金还钱... ... ”
[Pherwani] 'Either you organise funds...'
要么让印度国家银行给 BRs
...or ask Grindlays to give BRs.
听着，我明白
Look, I've understood the problem.
请相信我
Please trust me.
[ DT ]“市场势必会做出反应”
[DT] 'The market was bound to react.'
他承认自己是你文章里的大公牛
His whole confession of him being the Big Bull from your article...
只是另一个”哈沙德・梅塔是个骗子”的把戏
...is just another "Harshad Mehta is a liar" trick.
[ DT ]“我告诉你，他已经面临着巨大的损失”
[DT] 'I'm telling you, he's already looking at huge losses.'
你认为即使在市场上出现这样的损失..
Do you think even after making such losses in the market...
他会停下来吗? 他不会停下来的
...he is going to stop? He's not going to stop.
不，你说得对他不会..
No, you're right. He's not...
除非你能证明这整个行动都是违法的
...unless you prove that this entire activity is illegal.
现在看起来哈沙德从银行贷了款
Now, it seems like Harshad took a loan from the bank...
他把它还回去了
...and he returned it.
虽然有点晚了
Albeit, a bit late.
如果我们改变问题本身呢？
What if we change the question itself?
也许到那时就很难回答了？
Maybe then it will be difficult to answer?
听着，如果人们认为这是一笔50亿卢比的贷款，那没关系
Look, if people think it was a loan of 500 crores, that's okay.
但回到这个问题上，他是从哪里在这么短的时间内得到50亿卢比的呢？
But to return that, where did he get 500 crores in such a short time?
他有足够的资产，他人脉真的很广
He has enough assets, holdings. He literally knows everyone.
[ DT ]“我的意思是... ... 半个德里的人都跟着他的调子跳舞”
[DT] 'I mean... half of Delhi dances to his tune.'
对，没错，所以他肯定给了他们什么好处对吧？
Right. Exactly. So, he must've sold something, right?
但他没有官方说法是，高摩资本没有做任何交易
But he didn't. Officially, Growmore has not done any deals.
[ Sucheta ]“这是50亿卢比的问题”
[Sucheta] 'It's a matter of 500 crores.'
市场上的每个人都会知道这件事
'Everybody in the market would get to know about it.'
你是说他去了另一家银行？
Are you saying, he went to another bank?
如果 SBI 是……
If SBI was f*...
被他愚弄了
...fooled by him.
那么他一定重复了同样的事情..
Then he must have repeated the same thing...
一次又一次地和其他几家银行合作
...with several other banks again and again.
不是吧
B******t.
好吧
Okay.
你能查出他去了哪家银行吗？
Do you think you can find out which banks he has gone to?
我明白你的意思但是..
I get your point, but...
你要银行的名字做什么？
...what will you do with just the name of the bank?
我想再刊登一个标题..
I want to print just one more headline...
一篇可以永远铭刻在人们的脑海里的标题
...that will get imprinted in people's minds forever.
我需要另一个贝拉里抓住这头大公牛的角
I need another Bellary to grab this Big Bull by his horns.
梅塔先生，我们正在讨论延长信贷期限的问题
'Mr Mehta, we are talking about an extended line of credit.'
“在目前情况下... ... ”
'Under the present circumstances...'
“主席不可能给你这么多钱”
'...it is impossible for Grindlays to give you this kind of money. '
然后另一个选择是印度国家银行
Then the other option is that Grindlays gives BRs to NHB...
给NHB付的钱提供 BRs
...for the money that they have paid.
你这么说真有意思
It's funny you say that.
我们记入所有的 NHB 支票到您的帐户
We credited all the NHB cheques into your account.
我说的就是把价值50亿的 BRs 给 NHB
See, all I am saying is to give BRs worth 500 crores to NHB.
他们只是需要它来记录
They just need it for documentation purposes.
这只是一张纸，对吗？
And it's just a piece of paper, right?
这不仅仅是一张纸，不再是了
It's not just a piece of paper. Not any longer.
我们有严格的指示要求停止所有的安全交易
We have strict instructions to stop all security transactions.
随时都有可能进行审计
There could be an audit any day.
这真的这么急吗? 今天是星期天
And is this really this urgent? It's Sunday.
我不想在星期天谈生意
I don't wanna talk business on a Sunday.
我明白
I understand that.
事实上，我只是来打高尔夫球的
In fact, I just came here to play some golf.
我看见你在这儿，所以想到要讨论一下
I saw you here, so thought of discussing.
梅塔先生，你为什么不试试呢？
Well, why don't you try a shot, Mr. Mehta?
好啊
Why not?
有时候，你必须更加小心谨慎
Sometimes, you have to be more delicate.
看起来你好像不会打高尔夫球
It looks like you don't know how to play golf.
是的，我经常打板球
Yeah, I play cricket a lot.
我想我需要伸展一下我的身体
I think I need to stretch my body a little bit.
梅塔先生，是你的大脑没注意到球
Mr. Mehta, your mind missed the shot.
不是你的身体
Not your body.
也许，你应该坚持玩你擅长的游戏
Maybe, you should just stick to the game you are good at.
哈沙德，我们已经从煎锅掉进火里了
Harshad, we've fallen out of the frying pan into the fire.
我们没必要再坚持了
We don't need to hold our holdings till they hatch.
让我们清理 NHB 的证券
Let's clear NHB's settlement.
它不是任何其他私人银行，而是印度储备银行的一部分
It's not any other private bank. It's a part of RBI.
那个行长，他已经对你很生气了
And that governor, he's already pissed at you.
卖掉所有股份，结束这一切
Sell the holdings and end this.
我听说现在你可以在家里建一个高尔夫球场？
I've heard that these days you can set up a golf green at home?
你自己去查，我们也可以建一个
You find out. We'll get one too.
如果我们必须玩他们的游戏，我们就必须学会它，对不对？
If we have to play their game we'll have to learn it, right?
他怎么说？
What was that he said?
“你必须小心谨慎”
"You have to be delicate."
当你和我在一起的时候，我为什么要害怕？
Why should I be scared when you are with me?
如果遇到暴徒..
What will I do single-handedly if some goons...
这里有所有的名单
This has all the names.
“我从高摩资本拿到了名单”
'I got the list from Growmore.'
谢谢
Thanks.
不用谢，但我的名字不能出现在任何地方
Okay, but my name mustn't appear anywhere.
- 我的工作岌岌可危-我甚至不知道你的名字
- My job will be at stake. - I don't even know your name.
我怎么能泄露出去呢? 别担心
How can I leak it? And don't worry.
我知道怎么保护我的线人，你的名字不会暴露的
I know how to protect my sources. Your name won't be revealed.
好吧
Okay.
走吧，叔叔，今晚就到这里吧
Let's go, uncle. That's enough for tonight.
先生，哈尔沙德的 SBI 骗局根本算不了什么
Sir, Harshad's SBI scam is nothing.
每家银行在证券方面都有一些不规范之处
Every bank has some irregularities with regard to securities.
- 我觉得...-高希..
-[Ghosh] 'I think that...' - Ghosh...
涉及金额有多大？
How big is it? Number?
先生，这些账簿都乱七八糟的
Sir, the books are in a complete mess.
得到确切的数字需要时间，先生
It'll take time to figure out the exact number, sir.
那你还在等什么? 快点
What are you waiting for? Get on with this.
这是所有银行的名单..
This is the list of all the banks...
过去几天哈沙德一直在和他们打交道
...with whom Harshad was dealing for the past few days.
- 然后呢?-然后... 然后..
- And? - And... So...
有人能给我们一些线索吗？
...is there anyone, who can give us some leads?
我是说在这些银行工作的人？
I mean, someone who works in any of these banks?
”我们” ？
"Us"?
你是说能给”你”提供线索的人对吧？
Oh, you mean, someone who can give "you" a lead, right?
德布，这对我们俩来说都是潜在的共同线索
Debu, this is a potential common lead for both of us.
之后你可以写一篇详细的，经过深入研究的文章
You can write a detailed, and well-researched article later.
但是我需要尽快报道这个故事
But I need to break this story as soon as possible.
- 但如果你不想帮我...-好吧... 好吧..
- But if you don't wanna help me... - Okay... Okay...
我会找人告诉我们细节，好吗？
I'll look for someone who can get us the details. Okay?
好的，谢谢
Okay, thank you.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我想你们也该走了
I think you gentlemen should also leave now.
先生，您也应该休息一下，您的压力太大了
Sir, you should also rest. You are taking a lot of stress.
当然，我做完这个就回家
Yes, of course, I'll just finish this and go home.
要我们收拾桌子吗？
Should we clear the table?
不用了，我自己能行
No. I'll manage.
-去吧-晚安，先生
- Carry on. - Good night, sir.
很快，就是早安了
Soon, it will be Good Morning.
辛苦了
Anyway, thank you.
[ Venkitarajan ]“很抱歉这么早打扰您，先生”
[Venkitarajan] 'Sorry to disturb you so early in the morning, sir.'
但我们的估计是正确的
But our estimates were right.
我们团队的初步调查有结果了
My team has just come back after the preliminary enquiries and...
是的
Yes.
这是印度最大的金融骗局
It is India's biggest financial scam.
五百亿卢比
Five thousand crores.
但是..
But...
是的，先生... 我明白，但是..
Yes, sir... I do understand, but...
唯一的解决办法就是公之于众
Sir, the only way to handle this is to make it public.
是的... 当然
Y-Yes... of course.
是的，先生我会保密的是的
Yes, sir. I will keep it discreet. Yes.
谢谢你，先生
Thank you, sir.
对不起... 我睡着了... 你找到人了吗？
Sorry... I slept... Did you find anyone?
是吗? 你找到人了吗？
Yes? Did you find anyone?
给你
Here.
我没有
I didn't.
但新闻出版社做到了
But News Press did.
[ Debashis ]“根据消息来源，骗局的程度... ... ”
[Debashis] "According to the sources, the extent of the scam..."
“ ... 预计在200亿里亚尔左右”
"...is expected to be in the region of Rs. 2000 crores."
“他们怀疑，剩下的300亿卢比缺口... ... ”
"And they suspect that the remaining 3000 crores gap..."
” ... 可能是由于银行，包括某些证券... ”
"...is probably caused by banks including certain securities..."
“ ... 在他们的报告中，可能没有记录到SGL中”
"...in their report that may not be part of the SGL records."
新闻出版社从哪里得到这些细节？
Where is News Press getting these details?
我的意思是... 在过去的十天里我已经和一百个人交谈过了..
I mean... I've spoken to a hundred people in the last ten days...
没有人透露任何信息
...and no one's even uttered a word.
他们可能有一些机密消息来源
They may have some confidential source.
所有的资料来源都不像你的线人 ，对吧？
All the sources are not like your 'Karamchand', right?
是的
No.
这个消息来源于体制内的高层
It's a major source. Someone in the system, and very senior.
他们钓到了一些大鱼
They've netted some big fish.
这条大鱼张开了嘴
And this big fish has opened his mouth.
“先生，我希望你看了新闻”
[Ghosh] 'Sir, I hope you read the news.'
是的
Yeah.
- 先生，德里现在很恐慌-早上好
- Sir, Delhi is in panic. - Good morning.
财政部长办公室一直在不停地打电话
The finance minister's office has been calling incessantly.
- 他们有什么要说的?-他们没说什么
- What do they have to say? - Sir, nothing much.
他们只想和你说话，先生
They'll only speak with you, sir.
好吧，我来处理
Alright, I'll handle it.
这种情况以前从未发生过，先生
This has never happened before, sir.
印度储备银行行长召开新闻发布会
I mean, the RBI governor holding a press conference...
回应报纸上的一篇文章
...in reply to a newspaper article.
这可能引起更多的猜测和更多的问题
This could give rise to more speculation and more questions.
是媒体，他们肯定会问问题的
It's the Press, they are bound to ask questions.
此外，可能还有一些问题... ..
And moreover, there could be some questions...
我们可能无法回答
...which we might not have answers to.
你不需要回答每一个问题
[Man1] 'You need not answer every single question.'
“你只需要否认这个骗局的规模如此之大”
'You just need to deny that the scam is of such proportions.'
500亿是个震撼人心的数字
'5000 crores is a number that can shake anyone.'
只要向他们解释... ..
'Just explain to them...'
’ ... 骗局没有这篇文章... ’
'...that the scam is not as big...'
所说的那么大
'...as this article says.'
老实说，先生，我怎么能这么做呢？
Honestly, sir, how can I do this?
我凭什么否认事实？
I mean, on what basis do I deny so many facts? Huh?
我的意思是，我怎么能欺骗公众呢？
I mean, how can I deny something that is the truth?
现在... 现在在我的认知里
Something that is now... now in my knowledge.
总督先生，总理将会..
[Man1] 'Mr. Governor, the Prime Minister will be...'
“ ... 如果这样的消息伤害了我们的经济改革，我们会非常难办”
'...very upset if such news hurts our economic reforms.'
“请让我们想出一个办法来驳斥这些指控”
'Please, let us figure out a way how to refute these allegations.'
是的，先生，我明白
Yeah... Yes, sir. I understand.
“梅塔先生的最新情况如何? ”
[Man1] 'And what's the update on Mr. Mehta?'
嗯... 是的，调查也在进行中
Uhm... Yes. That investigation is on too.
很好，这应该是我们的重点
'Good. That should be our focus.'
好的，先生
Right, sir.
梅塔先生给你的支票
The cheques that Mr. Mehta gave you...
- 那些...-那些支票已经兑现了
- Those... - Those cheques have been cleared.
那么，你也把它们从你的账本上清除了吗？
So, have you cleared them off your books too?
什么意思？
Meaning?
也就是说，你没有支票，但你必须登记明细账
Meaning, you don't have the cheques, but you must have the details?
[穆克吉]‘给我看看记录’
[Mukherjee] 'Show me the records.'
这里
There's Mr. Mehta.
听着，他在我们这有个账户，他和我们做生意，他可以..
Look, he has an account with us, he does business with us. He can...
他想取多少钱都可以
He can always withdraw as much money as he wants to.
但是你把钱转到他的账户上了，对吧？
But you transfer the money to his account, right?
所以也许你可以给我们看看..
So, maybe you would like to show us...
转到他的个人账户上吗？
...the transactions to his personal accounts then?
不，不，我不是那个意思
No, no, I don't mean that.
我的意思是..
What I mean is that...
几天前他做了一笔即期交易
...he had brokered a ready-forward transactions a few days back.
所以钱是打到他账户上的，他肯定用过了
So, the money came to his account. He must've used it...
用于其他目的
...for some other purposes.
那你是和谁做的这个远期交易？
And who did you do this ready-forward transaction with?
作为国家中央银行..
As the central bank of the country...
我们断然否认这个骗局的严重性
...we categorically deny that the scam is of such proportions.
具体细节到等
The details would only be known...
经过 RBI 小组的全面调查
...after a full investigation by the RBI team...
这些银行的证券资产
...into the security holdings of these banks.
所以在那之前我请求你不要..
So, till then, I request you not to...
盲目的报道
...blindly speculate, and...
让有关当局做他们的工作
...let the concerned authorities do their job.
先生，你是怎么得出结论的
Sir, how did you arrive at the conclusion...
骗局没有500亿卢比吗？
...that the scam is not 5,000 crores?
我们知道体制内部出了问题
We know that there's a problem in unit 64.
- 你搞定了吗?-还没
- Have you sorted it out? - Not yet.
你知道债券存在多少问题吗？
Do you know how much problem exists in bonds?
- 损失有多大?-我们正在计算
- What is the extent of that loss? - We're calculating that.
你到底知不知道假BRs
Do you even know the extent of fake BRs...
... 在市场上的流通成都，行长先生？
...that are circulating in the market, Mr. Governor?
“你有没有意识到这样一个事实，假冒的 BRs 已经几乎... ... ”
[Reporter 1] 'Have you been aware of the fact that fake BRs have been almost...'
- ... 成为一个既定的市场惯例?-我们正在进行审计
- ...an established market practice? - We're conducting an audit.
先生，你知道投资组合资金是怎么回事吗？
Sir, do you know what was happening with portfolio money?
为什么公共服务单位会有这么多钱进来？
Why was so much money from PSUs coming in?
- 计算好了吗?-还没有
- Have those calculations been made? - Not yet.
那你凭什么说这个骗局不是500亿？
Then on what basis are you saying that the scam is not 5,000 crores?
- 你为什么不重视这个骗局?-听着这只是个估计
- Why are you downplaying the scam? - Look, this is just an estimation.
[ Venkitarajan ]“这是我们的理解”
[Venkitarajan] 'This is our understanding.'
我们是专家，让我们来做我们的工作
We are the specialists and we know our job.
那么，行长先生，你觉得你对此毫无头绪
So, Mr. Governor, you are admitting that you have no clue.
然而，你却坚信这个数字不可能是500亿卢比
Yet, you are adamant about the fact that the amount cannot be 5,000 crores.
我们要保护的是谁？
Who are we trying to protect here?
对不起，记者会结束了，谢谢
Sorry, no more questions. Thank you.
先生， NHB？
Sir, NHB?
一方面，我们试图保住颜面
On the one hand, we are trying to save face to contain the havoc...
并且减少这个骗局造成的损失
...that this scam has created.
另一方面..
And on the other...
是印度储备银行的全资子公司
...NHB, which is a wholly-owned subsidiary of the RBI...
给哈萨德送钱来保护他
...is rolling out cash to Harshad to save his back!
梅塔拿整个系统开了个玩笑
Mehta has made a joke of this system.
先生，你认为菲尔瓦尼先生也参与了吗？
Sir, do you think Mr. Pherwani might also be involved?
我倒愿意相信他与此事无关
Well, I'd like to believe he's not involved.
但是像这样的机构..
But when an institution like the...
... NHB 处理如此大量的交易..
...NHB deals in such high volume transactions...
他不可能不知情
...can't be without Pherwani's nod.
先生，你为什么不直接跟他谈谈？
Sir, why don't you speak to him directly?
我们必须找到一个更聪明的方法来处理这个问题
We have to find a smarter way to deal with this.
[拉吉迪普]“尽管他否认... ... ”
[Rajdeep] "Despite his denial..."
印度储备银行行长
"...the RBI governor was unable to answer a single question..."
连记者的一个问题都回答不了
"...from the press satisfactorily."
“这个骗局反映了银行体系的腐败... ... ”
"The scam is a reflection of the rot in the banking system..."
“ ... 以及印度储备银行监管不力”
"...and the inadequate monitoring by the RBI."
“市场的某些领域对印度储备银行”
"Certain sections of the market are extremely critical..."
”的徒劳调查极为关键”
"...of the ham-handed investigation of the RBI..."
” ... 因为他们相信政府只是想... ”
"...as they believe that the government is simply trying..."
” ... 把事情掩盖起来... ”
"...to sweep the matter under the carpet..."
” ... 越来越多的骷髅可能会从壁橱里滚出来”
"...as more skeletons are likely to tumble out of the closet."
所以，现在我们也把印度央行行长变成了一个恶棍？
So, now we're also turning the RBI governor into a villain?
如果你不想发表这篇文章
If you don't want to publish this, why don't I give you the transcript...
那我直接把发布会的整个过程全部发表出来？
...of the entire press conference and you can print that?
不，我更喜欢这个
No, I like this better.
- 谢谢-继续写完
- Thank you. - Finish it.
这咖啡是怎么回事！
What's with this coffee!
太难喝了
It's terrible.
今天，反对派再一次... ..
'Today, once again, the opposition...'
“ ... 在议会中制造噪音... ”
'...made a noise in the parliament...'
关于价值500亿卢比的违法行为
'...about irregularities worth 5000 crores...'
印度储备银行行长的新闻发布会也受到质疑
'RBI Governor's press conference was also questioned...'
有人要求成立一个联合委员会
'...and there were demands For a Joint Parliamentary Committee...'
“ ... 对此事进行调查... ”
'...to carry out investigations in this matter...'
财政部长向反对派保证... ..
'The finance minister assured the opposition...'
政府将很快进行公正的法律调查
'...that the government will soon conduct an unbiased legal investigation.'
印度时报再一次发挥了作用
Once again, TOI is making a difference.
不是每个人都有胆量站起来反对梅塔先生..
Not everyone will have had the guts to first go against Mr. Mehta...
然后是印度储备银行行长
...and then, the RBI governor.
-苏切塔!-[鼓掌]
- Sucheta! -[applauds]
苏切塔，我已经送给你足够多的书了
Sucheta, I've gifted you enough books.
下次，我得送你一些酒杯
Next time, I will have to gift you some wine glasses.
那你为什么还不送呢？
So why haven't you?
你总是在这里
You're always here.
无论如何，德布 · 莫沙伊..
Anyway, Debu Moshai...
为什么要喝酒？
...what's the occasion for wine?
[ Sucheta ]“这篇文章在议会引起了轩然大波? ”
[Sucheta] 'The uproar that the article caused in the parliament?'
议会的喧嚣不是什么大事
Uproar in the parliament is no big deal.
- 嗯?-总是这样
- Hmm? - That always happens.
- 他们是政客-嗯
- They're politicians. - Hmm.
尖叫是他们工作的一部分
Screaming is part of their job profile.
他们简历上要写分贝值的
Decibel levels are at the top on their CVs...
证明声音有多大
...confirming how loud they can be...
不管怎样，先不说这个..
Anyway, leaving that aside...
我们提前庆祝
We are celebrating in advance.
虽然新闻明天就要发表了
Though the news will be published tomorrow.
这个值得庆祝的消息是什么？
What's this celebration-worthy news?
印度储备银行已经成立了一个委员会来调查这个骗局
RBI has formed a committee to investigate the scam.
该委员会将由印度储备银行副行长 r. Janakiraman 领导
And it will be headed by... RBI deputy governor R. Janakiraman.
不错嘛！
Not bad!
所以政府终于承认他们有问题了
So the government is finally acknowledging that they have a problem.
正式的
Officially.
- 不错-等等..
- Not bad. - Wait...
先别喝酒，我还没有告诉你主要的独家新闻呢
Don't drink yet. I haven't told you the main exclusive news yet.
什么独家新闻? 听着我是记者..
What exclusive news? Listen, I'm the journalist...
谁应该得到独家新闻
...who's supposed to get exclusive news.
是的，但我也有我的消息来源
Yes, but I too have my sources.
我也有自己的线人
I too have my own... 'Karamchand'.
好吧，抱歉
Okay, sorry.
政府已经同意将调查移交给 CBI..
The government has agreed to hand over the investigation to the CBI...
将由一名高级军官领导
...and it will be headed by a top rank officer.
CBI? 他们是认真的？
CBI? They've gotten serious, huh?
我也是认真的
I'm serious too.
是吗？
Are you?
关于什么？
What about?
- 什么事?-Venkitarajan 先生
- Yes? - Mr. Venkitarajan.
菲尔瓦尼先生
Pherwani, here.
“我听说... ... ”
[Pherwani] 'I've heard...'
你们办公室的几个人在查我们的账目？
...few men from your office are trying to look into our books?
菲尔瓦尼先生，那些不是你的账目
Mr. Pherwani, those are not your books.
你好像忘了..
You seem to have forgotten that...
“ NHB 是 RBI 的子公司”
[Venkitarajan] '...NHB is a subsidiary of RBI.'
你不能就这样帮助你的朋友
You can't help your friends just like that.
[ Pherwani ]“不... 不是那样的”
[Pherwani] 'No... It was not like that.'
这只是一个简单的即期交易，仅此而已
It was a simple ready-forward deal, that's all.
菲尔瓦尼先生
Mr. Pherwani...
很晚了，我得睡觉了
It's late. I need to get some sleep.
我们能晚点再谈这个吗？
Can we talk about this later?
呃... Venkitarajan 先生..
Uh... Mr. Venkitarajan...
我有个建议
I have a suggestion.
[ Pherwani ]‘允许哈尔沙德延期还债... ... ’
[Pherwani] 'Allow Harshad to roll over his dues...'
... 再过两个星期
...for another fortnight.
然后你就可以安心睡觉了
And then you will sleep in peace.
[ Venkitarajan ]“达斯先生，我并不是无缘无故地把你叫到这里来”
[Venkitarajan] 'Mr. Das, I haven't called you here without a reason.'
我有充分的理由... ..
'I must be having a very good reason...'
直接给调查局局长打电话对吗
'...to call the chief of CBI directly, right?'
我们成立的委员会正在调查这个骗局..
This committee that we're setting up to investigate this scam...
我们需要一些额外的帮助
...we'll need some additional help.
有太多的人参与其中
You see, there are too many parties involved.
太多黑幕交易
Too many underhand dealings that are not above board.
还有..
And...
很多复杂的高级交易
...too many complex, high-level transactions.
我们需要清理系统
We need to clean the system.
为此，我们需要确凿的证据
And for that, we need hard evidence.
没有证据我们什么也做不了
We can't do anything without the evidence.
我们将彻底调查此事
We will investigate it thoroughly.
但调查局从未处理过..
But CBI has never handled...
... 这样一个经济案件
...such a financial case.
我们需要你的团队不断..
We'll need your team to constantly...
支持我们，引导我们
...back us up and guide us at every step.
当然
Absolutely.
我们与你同在
We are with you.
我们所要求的只是..
All that we ask for is...
一个好警官来处理这个案子
...a good officer to handle the investigation.
一个真正的好警官
A really good officer.
我会给你我最好的
I'll give you the best I have.
-马达文-马……
- Madhavan. - Ma...
博福斯 · 马达文？
Bofors Madhavan?
是的
Yes. Same officer.
太棒了
Well...